# Oliver Earl









# Summary

Courteous and self-motivated software engineer and former computer science teacher, with multiple years specialising in the PHP and JavaScript full-stack ecosystems and is passionate for writing test-driven, enterprise-ready code and documentation to produce innovative and performative software running on the web and beyond.

# WORK EXPERIENCE

#### Software Developer, Stickee Technology

Jan 2021 - Present

- Responsible for high quality, test-backed full-stack code; providing both support and new functionality both independently and collaboratively across the Digital Delivery team.
- Lead developer on the full-stack integration of an alternative payment provider and monthly payment plan support for mobile phones and accessories for a major UK phone network.
- Primary contributor for various internal PHP and Laravel packages, most notably a fork of the popular Spatie Activity Log package to support older versions of the framework, provide automated alerts, and database ID correlation, all with full documentation and continuous integration.
- Routinely develop and/or utilise APIs, automatic asynchronous file-based importing and processing, component-based front-end design, and comprehensive, data-set driven testing suites.

### Volunteer Software Developer, Nightline Association

Mar 2022 - Present

- Core developer on Portal, our bespoke software leveraging Laravel and Inertia.js to provide modular services including call logging, real-time anonymous instant messaging, and data analysis to the charity and to student-run Nightlines operating across the UK.
- Responsible for ensuring continued quality code and documentation, and aiding with the mentoring and on-boarding of junior developers, including code reviewing and organising pair programming sessions.
- Assists with the support and maintenance of internal WordPress plugins, our anonymous email suite written in Java, and sparingly used legacy projects using CodeIgniter 3.

#### Teacher of Computer Science and IT, Arden Academy

Jan 2020 - Dec 2021

Taught GCSE and A-Level Computer Science at one of the top state schools in the UK.

**Demonstrator**, Aberystwyth University

Sep 2015 - Sep 2019

Part-time teaching assistant on modules including topics such as Arduino C++, Linux, and JavaScript.

### Front-End Developer Intern, Amadeus Germany GmbH

Jun 2016 - Dec 2016

Prototyped front-ends using then cutting-edge TypeScript and Angular. Working language of German.

## Technical Skills

Software Engineering	RESTful APIs, GraphQL, Design Patterns, Data Structures and Algorithms,		
	Agile Methodologies, SDLC, Jira, Confluence, Wrike, Trello, G-Suite		
Full-Stack Development	PHP, HTML/CSS, JavaScript, TypeScript, jQuery, Sass, Bootstrap, Tailwind,		
	Vue.js 2.x/3.x, Vuex, Pinia, Nuxt.js, Inertia.js, WordPress, CodeIgniter 3		
Laravel Ecosystem	Laravel 5.6 - 9.x, Lumen, Nova, Cashier, Echo, Composer Package Development		
Game Development	Phaser.js, Godot, Photoshop, Krita, Aesprite		
Testing and Tools	PHPUnit, Pest, Dusk, Jest, PHP CS Fixer / Pint, Eslint, Pusher, Websockets,		
	MySQL, Redis, Docker, Git, GitHub Actions, Linux, Java, Bash, Virtualisation		

# EDUCATION

2019 - 2020	PGCE Post-Compulsory	Education, Birmingham	City University	(Qualified)

2018 - 2019 MSc Software Engineering, Aberystwyth University (Merit)

2014 - 2018 BSc(Hons) Computer Science w/ German, Aberystwyth University (1st Class)

# **PROJECTS**

#### ExtraContinue

github.com/extracontinue

Following a bout of severe illness, ExtraContinue came about as an idea for a dead man's switch that can perform actions such as sending emails, instant messages, and tweets, after a long period of unexpected inactivity. Still under active development.

Fluent interface for working with SplFixedArrays github.com/petrobolos/fixed-array-functions An open source library that provides a fluent interface and helper functions for working with fixed-size arrays, written for PHP 8.1.

# Hashnode API Wrapper

github.com/oliverearl/php-hashnode

A wrapper for conveniently interfacing Hashnode's GraphQL API, compatible with PHP 7.4 and above.

## Publications

#### Personal Blog

oliverearl.co.uk/posts

Periodically updated with posts on software engineering, professional development, and pedagogy.

# OTHER EXPERIENCE

#### Regional Coordinator, Nightline Association

Jun 2021 - Present

The elected representative responsible for overseeing Nightline branches within Wales, ensuring that they operate within the guidelines set by the central organisation and are adequately supported with their day-to-day operations.

#### Listening Volunteer, Aberystwyth Nightline

Feb 2015 - Sep 2019

Volunteer with more than 600 hours of helpline support, 550 in peer-to-peer support, and 230 in Active Listening training. Certified in both mental health first aid and applied suicide intervention.

# REFERENCES

Available on request.